Guide to the Prison Education Program Research Lab Oral Histories on Debt and Incarceration TAM.816
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Prison Education Program Research Lab Oral Histories on Debt and Incarceration
2019-2021
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York University. Prison Education Program
Bardelli, Tommaso
TAM.816
3.6 Megabytes in 25 documents
Founded in 2018, the Prison Education Program (PEP) Research Lab is a collaboration between faculty and formerly incarcerated students at New York University conducting research on the financial and human costs of mass incarceration in New York State. Students with lived experiences of incarceration are hired by the Lab, and trained by faculty members in the methods and ethics of social research. Formerly incarcerated researchers take part in all aspects of the research, from identifying research questions to design, data collection, and dissemination. By drawing on researchers from New York communities most affected by incarceration, the PEP Research Lab aims to amplify their voices and concerns, and to generate grounded policy recommendations and advocacy initiatives around responsible decarceration in the city and the state. NYU professors Julie Livingston (Social and Cultural Analysis and History), Thuy Linh Tu (Social and Cultural Analysis) and Andrew Ross (Social and Cultural Analysis) started the Debt and Incarceration oral history project in the fall of 2018. Working with PEP students Joshua Barreto, José Diaz, Derick McCarthy, and Vincent Thompson, Livingston, Tu and Ross began conducting in-depth interviews with formerly incarcerated New Yorkers about the financial challenges they faced after release. In particular, those conversations focused on narrators' experiences with financial debt and on how their, often significant, debt burden was connected with incarceration. The Prison Education Program Research Lab Oral Histories on Debt and Incarceration (dated 2019-2021) consists of pdf oral history transcripts created by the PEP Research Lab. The majority of the anonymized interview transcripts in this collection were conducted as part of a PEP study on the commissary system in New York State prisons led by Tommaso Bardelli, Thuy Linh Tu, and Zachary Gillespie. The interviews document the multiple financial costs people face to cover basic needs during their incarceration. In an additional effort Bardelli, Tu, and Gillespie interviewed over 60 formerly incarcerated New Yorkers who had been released from male prison facilities in New York State within the past four years about their experiences with the commissary system and other forms of consumer spending in prison. These interviews document how decades of fiscal austerity, and the privatization of basic services within the prison system progressively shifted the economic costs of incarceration onto prisoners and their families. They also shed light on the pervasive impact of austerity policies on the realities of carceral punishment, the extension of the carceral state into the lives of individuals and families, sites of incarceration as sites of financial extraction, and the everyday lives of incarcerated individuals.
Scope and Contents
The Prison Education Program Research Lab Oral Histories on Debt and Incarceration (dated 2019-2021) consists of pdf oral history transcripts created by the New York University Prison Education Program (PEP) Research Lab. The majority of the anonymized interview transcripts in this collection were conducted as part of a PEP study on the commissary system in New York State prisons led by Tommaso Bardelli, Thuy Linh Tu, and Zachary Gillespie. The interviews document the multiple financial costs people face to cover basic needs during their incarceration. In an additional effort Bardelli, Tu, and Gillespie interviewed over 60 formerly incarcerated New Yorkers who had been released from male prison facilities in New York State within the past four years about their experiences with the commissary system and other forms of consumer spending in prison. These interviews document how decades of fiscal austerity, and the privatization of basic services within the prison system progressively shifted the economic costs of incarceration onto prisoners and their families. They also shed light on the pervasive impact of austerity policies on the realities of carceral punishment, the extension of the carceral state into the lives of individuals and families, sites of incarceration as sites of financial extraction, and the everyday lives of incarcerated individuals. The collection also includes transcripts of three conversations reflecting on the research process and project.
Arrangement
Interviews are arranged numerically by anonymized narrator number.
Conditions Governing Access
Donor permission is required for access. Those wishing to consult the collection, either within the reading room or remotely, must complete a brief survey prior to accessing the collection. Requests to view or use collection material outside of the reading room-- inclusive of downloadable PDFs files or printed copies-- must be approved by the PEP Research Lab. Please contact the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated in October 2022 by Tommasso Bardelli on behalf of the Prison Education Program Research Lab; the accession number associated with this gift is 2022.084.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Historical Note
Founded in 2018, the Prison Education Program (PEP) Research Lab is a collaboration between faculty and formerly incarcerated students at NYU conducting research on the financial and human costs of mass incarceration in New York State. Students with lived experiences of incarceration are hired by the Lab, and trained by faculty members in the methods and ethics of social research. Formerly incarcerated researchers take part in all aspects of the research, from identifying research questions to design, data collection, and dissemination. By drawing on researchers from New York communities most affected by incarceration, the PEP Research Lab aims to amplify their voices and concerns, and to generate grounded policy recommendations and advocacy initiatives around responsible decarceration in the city and the state.
NYU professors Julie Livingston (Social and Cultural Analysis and History), Thuy Linh Tu (Social and Cultural Analysis) and Andrew Ross (Social and Cultural Analysis) started the Debt and Incarceration oral history project in the fall of 2018. Working with PEP students Joshua Barreto, José Diaz, Derick McCarthy, and Vincent Thompson, Livingston, Tu and Ross began conducting in-depth interviews with formerly incarcerated New Yorkers about the financial challenges they faced after release. In particular, those conversations focused on narrators' experiences with financial debt and on how their, often significant, debt burden was connected with incarceration. After conducting those initial interviews, the Lab's researchers launched a series of studies on the relationship between debt and incarceration in New York City, documenting different forms of carceral debt – from prison commissary and telecommunication costs to traffic fines and predatory auto loans.
Most of the interviews included in the present collection were conducted as part of a study on the commissary system in New York State prisons. The study was led by Tommaso Bardelli, who had joined the Lab as a postdoctoral fellow in September 2019, Thuy Linh Tu, and Zach Gillespie, an NYU PEP student majoring in American Studies. By focusing on the prison commissary system, their goal was to shed light on the multiple financial costs people face just to cover basic needs during their incarceration. Between October 2019 and September 2020, Bardelli, Tu, and Gillespie interviewed over 60 formerly incarcerated New Yorkers about their experiences with commissary and other forms of consumer spending in prison.
The collection includes a total of 25 transcripts of interviews conducted by Lab's researchers. Transcripts 001, 002, 003, 004, 006, 007, 010 are from the first series of exploratory interviews about the commissary system, which Bardelli and Tu collected with PEP students and alumni during the fall of 2019. Those interviews were conducted in person on NYU Washington Square campus. Transcripts numbered from 106 to 134, as well as 223 and 232, are part of the second series of commissary interviews with formerly incarcerated New Yorkers and their families (223, 232), collected between January and October 2020. Bardelli and Gillespie were the lead interviewers for this series, and all conversations were conducted remotely (via phone or video calling) due the COVID-19 pandemic.
Mass incarceration; Oral histories (literary works); Neoliberalism; Punishment; Imprisonment; Human rights.; Prisoners -- Civil rights; Prisons.; Privatization; Prison-industrial complex; Debt; New York University. Prison Education Program; Bardelli, Tommaso
- Narrator 001, 2019; cuid36507 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_1)
  Biographical Note
  Narrator 001 was in his early forties at the time of this interview. He had been released in 2018, after serving an 11 year sentence in New York State. Narrator 001 lived in Upstate New York and worked in the construction industry, while also pursuing his Bachelor's degree in professional studies.
  Scope and Contents
  In this interview, Narrator 001 talks about the state jobs he had during his incarceration, including in industry and the mess hall, and how he budgeted his income along with the money his family sent him. He recounts his experience purchasing items from the commissary store, including his interactions with clerks, other incarcerated men, and how far $30 got him per commissary. His account sheds light on the cost of food items in prison relative to the wages that incarcerated individuals receive for their labor.
- Narrator 002, 2019; cuid36508 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_2)
  Narrator 002 was released in the Fall of 2017, having served 11 years in New York State prisons. At the time of this interview Narrator 002 was in his early thirties and lived in the Bronx, New York. Having started his college education during his incarceration, Narrator 002 was now pursuing a Master's degree in American Studies.
  In this interview, Narrator 002 talks about the importance of food and commissary in prison not only for sustenance but also for maintaining relationships with other incarcerated men. He recounts his experience receiving packages from family members, gifting items to other incarcerated men, and exchanging cigarettes and stamps for items. His account sheds light on the social meaning and economic value of food items within the prison informal economy.
- Narrator 003, 2019; cuid36509 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_3)
  Narrator 003 was born in Brooklyn, New York. He was 26 years old at the time of this interview. After being incarcerated for three years in his early thirties, Narrator 003 returned to New York where he started his own private transportation company, while also working as a motivational speaker and an advocate for the formerly incarcerated. Narrator 003 holds an Associate degree in liberal arts, which he completed during his incarceration, and said he intended to pursue his Bachelor's degree in the near future.
  In this interview, Narrator 003 discusses how commissary works in prison, including the frequent delays, the particular items available for purchase, and the difficulty of surviving on commissary alone due to the high costs of shopping there. Narrator 003 describes how he tried to make use of packages from his mother to circumvent the restrictions on commissary purchases, and how he sought help from other family members and friends in order to avoid racking up debt inside prison. This interview sheds light on the financial difficulties of surviving in prison, the prevalence of debt, and the necessity of relying on family members for money and packages.
- Narrator 004, 2019; cuid36510 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_4)
  Narrator 004 was born and raised in New York City. He describes himself as a family man first. He was incarcerated for four years, and earned his Bachelor's degree shortly after his release. At the time this conversation was recorded, the narrator was pursuing a Master's degree and working as an educator and advocate with communities affected by mass incarceration in New York.
  In this interview, Narrator 004 describes how he had to rely on financial support from friends and family during his incarceration due to the high cost of commissary items and the low wages he earned through prison labor. He also recounts selling cigarettes and stamps in order to generate additional income in the prison informal economy. The interview sheds light on the functioning of the informal economy, including "inmate stores" and the drug trade, as well as the precarious conditions of life inside prison institutions.
- Narrator 006, 2019; cuid36511 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_5)
  Narrator 006 was born in New York City; he served seven and a half years in various New York State correctional institutions. At the time of this interview, the narrator was in his early thirties and pursuing a Bachelor's degree majoring in American Studies.
  In this interview, Narrator 006 talks about his job in the mess hall and how he generated a steady income through the prison informal economy to make up for the low wages he received for his labor inside prison. He recounts his experience cooking with other men to save money, receiving packages and money from his family, and taking on a "hustle." His account sheds light on the risks that incarcerated people take to acquire an adequate amount of food for their survival, and why they must do so.
- Narrator 007, 2019; cuid36512 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_6)
  Narrator 007 was born and raised in Brooklyn, New York. He completed his high school education and obtained an Associate degree in liberal arts while serving over a decade in New York prisons, before being released in 2019. Narrator 007 was in his late thirties at the time of this interview. He lived in the Bronx and worked as a personal trainer. He also hosted and produced his own podcast on incarceration and re-entry.
  In this interview, Narrator 007 talks about the state jobs he had during his incarceration, including in the mess hall and commissary store. He explains why he saved the money that his family sent him instead of spending it within the formal and informal prison economies. His account sheds light on the fees that incarcerated people are responsible for including surcharges, and the necessity of financial foresight.
- Narrator 010, 2020; cuid36513 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_7)
  Narrator 010 was born and raised in New York City. In October 2019, after serving 15 years in New York State prisons, he moved back to the Bronx, working as a harm reduction specialist in the borough. He described his job as "saving lives, every day." He hoped to continue working in this field in the future, and at the time of the interview he was pursuing a Master's degree in Social Work.
  In this interview, Narrator 010 discusses working in the mess hall during his incarceration and how the prison often cut back on portions and particular meals, which forced people to spend their money at the commissary store. He recounts price increases and product shortages at commissary, and talks about the help he received from his family, particularly his wife, in the form of money and packages. He explains that "side hustles" and participation in the prison informal economy are what help incarcerated people afford basic necessities, but that either could result in accrued debt and violent retaliation from other prisoners. This interview sheds light on the financial difficulty of surviving inside prison and how the informal economy is a lifeline to incarcerated individuals while also creating the potential for debt and violence.
- Narrator 106, 2020; cuid36514 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_8)
  Narrator 106 was in his mid-twenties at the time of this interview. He was born and raised in the Bronx, New York, where he returned in the winter of 2017, after serving three years in New York state prisons.
  In this interview, Narrator 106 discusses the differences in commissary between Rikers Island and state prison. In prison, his jobs as a porter and mess hall cleaner paid very little, but he was able to rely on monetary support from loved ones. Narrator 106 explains that he participated in the informal economy and sold drugs while he was incarcerated to take the financial burden off of his family, suggesting that surviving in prison is reminiscent of hustling on the streets. Narrator 106 also talks about the restrictions set by the prison and how they limited him in terms of receiving packages and money for commissary from loved ones long-distance and during visits. This interview sheds light on the necessity of outside financial support, and how many incarcerated people turn to hustling and other illicit means to get by.
- Narrator 108, 2019; cuid36515 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_9)
  Narrator 108 was born and raised in Brooklyn, New York. He was in his early thirties at the time of this interview. After serving a 13 years long sentence in New York State prisons, he was released in the early months of 2018. Since returning home, in Brooklyn, he works as a personal trainer and fitness instructor. He holds an Associate degree in liberal arts, which he completed while incarcerated.
  In this interview, Narrator 108 talks about the jobs he had during his incarceration, including in optics and the mess hall. He recounts the financial and emotional support he received from family, partners, and childhood friends, and how he maintained those relationships while he was in prison. He explains that each of his loved ones covered a different expense, including the phone, commissary buys, and packages. Though he received help from the outside, he did want to take care of his needs largely on his own. His account sheds light on what it is like to do prison labor.
- Narrator 110, 2019; cuid36516 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_10)
  Narrator 110 was born and raised in Harlem, New York City. After spending 7 and a half years in New York State prisons, he was released in the spring of 2018. After returning home, he got married and moved with his wife and four children to Georgia. In Georgia Narrator 110, who was 49 at the time of this interview, worked at a local saw mill factory, while hoping to start his own business in the near future.
  In this interview, Narrator 110 recounts his experience surviving in prison with irregular financial support from his family outside. He describes the food provided by the prison as insufficient and of extremely poor quality. To get some extra food, Narrator 110 had to carefully budget the little income he received through prison labor, and to rely on the solidarity of fellow prisoners.
- Narrator 112, 2020; cuid36517 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_11)
  Narrator 112 was born at Manhattan Hospital, in New York City, in 1975. At the time of the interview (Fall 2020), he had been living in Brooklyn for about two years, since being released from prison after serving a 13 years sentence in New York State. Since returning home, Narrator 112 worked for a maintenance company, doing work at different locations across Brooklyn. He spent most of his free time writing and composing hip hop music, a passion he cultivated from the time he was a young kid.
  In this interview, Narrator 112 talks about what it was like to be incarcerated and not being able to count on regular financial support from friends or family outside. He recounts experiencing constant hunger and other forms of extreme material deprivation during his incarceration. He also describes how he generated extra income in the prison informal economy to be able to purchase food and other essentials at commissary
- Narrator 113, 2020; cuid36518 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_12)
  Narrator 113 served nearly 20 years in New York State prisons, as well as five years of post release supervision. At the time of the interview, Narrator 113 was 50 years of age, and was employed as a supervisor at a 4 star hotel in New York City. He said that he hoped to start his own company in the health and wellness industry. He also planned to finish his college education, which he had started pursuing during his incarceration.
  In this interview, Narrator 113 talks about how he made ends meet during his incarceration by engaging in the prison informal economy. He recounts how he had to take on several "hustles", such as gambling, selling mess hall food, and trading cigarettes, in order to generate extra income. His account sheds light on several features of the prison informal economy, including the currencies, debt and credit, and its link with the outside economy.
- Narrator 114, 2020; cuid36519 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_13)
  Narrator 114 was born and raised in Nassau County, New York. At the time of this interview he was in his late 30s. He had just graduated from college, and finished his time under parole. After his release in 2017, Narrator 114 got married, and moved with his wife to Upstate New York, where he enjoyed hiking, photography and working out.
  In this interview, Narrator 114 discusses how he relied on his family to send him money in order to purchase items at the prison commissary, the initial delays he struggled with when it came to receiving his money, and that he did not know how commissary worked nor which essentials to buy. He explains that, although his jobs inside prison only paid cents per hour, he was able to benefit from certain perks in each role, including collecting and selling contraband. In addition, Narrator 114 sold tobacco and purchased drugs in the prison informal economy. This interview sheds light on the function of the informal economy inside prison, the importance of outside support, and the benefits of certain jobs.
- Narrator 122, 2020; cuid36520 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_816_ER_14)
  Narrator 122, who was born and raised in Staten Island, New York, was in his mid-thirties at the time of this interview. He had been released in January 2020, after serving over six years in New York State prisons. After coming home, Narrator 122 moved to New York, and was employed as a case-worker in a men's shelter in the city.